Leah: So, what do we mean when
we talk about security by design?
Security has often long been considered an afterthought in
the software development process, with measures to address
potential issues, typically tacked on just before release.
This can cause serious issues as components are
so interdependent and changing a single piece of
code could affect the whole application adversely.
Chris: The focus previously has on implementing
security controls around physical infrastructure such as
networks, servers and endpoints using firewalls, but this
approach, is no longer adequate in sustaining today's
expectations for rapid and reliable deployment of software.
Leah: In software development you will hear all about
the ‘software development lifecycle’, but you will
also encounter the ‘security by design lifecycle’.
Both of these terms are closely linked as the starting point
for both is the initial idea, which is then taken through
the stages of design, develop, test, deliver and support.
Chris: The difference between the two is that ‘Security
by design’ focuses on the requirements relating to
relevant security features such as data integrity,
authentication, confidentiality, authorisation and privacy.
Leah: Taking ‘security by design’ into consideration
at the very beginning of a project helps to
reduce costs and reduce the potential risks
that may be faced when the software is released.
Building security into the development process
and testing cycles, is good practice and can
save on costs, extra time and reliability.
This will in turn also help to maintain
client confidence in their product.
Chris: ‘Security by design’ is about having a risk-based
approach to development that focuses on continuous
assessment, analysis, improvement, and validation
to create safer practices and better safety nets.
Leah: An analogy that is often used in security
is the ‘Castle and Moat model’ that means
everyone inside the castle is protected.
Think of the moat and the drawbridge as
high-quality code that create that security and
the tack on elements are like the foot soldiers.
If the castle walls and the moat and drawbridge
are in good order, then the foot soldiers will only
be needed in emergencies or in case of a breach.
But failure to create a secure structure in the first place
and maintain it well, will result in cracks appearing which
even though they can be filled, will eventually give way!
Chris: Failure to incorporate security by design will
continue the cycle of further development, patches and
bug fixes as and when required which takes up further
time, resources and for those who are using the software
a potential lack of confidence in the software itself.